ESTHER NJERI MUNYIRI

P.O Box 48260-00100, GPO, Nairobi, Kenya | Tel: +254 (0)722 168 466 | Email: delmunyiri@gmail.com

COUNTRY MANAGER

Country Manager and Nursing Specialist, with over 13 years of progressive experience in providing strategic leadership on country operations, managing health projects and programs, and providing emergency and general nursing care.

Operations strategist with experience in managing and coordinating emergency response programs, including medical evacuations/repatriations and disease surveillance and outbreak management.

Stakeholder strategist, structuring collaboration and partnerships with public, private, and non-profit stakeholders including government ministries, county government, NGOs, and academic institutions.

Effective communicator, fluent in English and Kiswahili with advanced use of MS Office Suite.

Areas of Expertise

Strategic Planning & Execution | Operations Management | Emergency Nursing Care | General Nursing care | Project Management | Medical Evacuations | Strategic Partnerships | Capacity Building/Training | Team Leadership | Proposal Development | Fundraising | Budget Management | Project Reporting | Disease Surveillance & Outbreak Management | Infection Prevention & Control (IPC) | Quality Assurance | Research | Health Education

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Kenya Country Manager | Oxygen Hub

December 2021 - Present

Providing strategic leadership and direction in developing and implementing the Kenya Country strategy, managing franchisees in the Kenyan market, and supporting franchisees with go-to-market strategy development, business development, customer acquisition, sales operations, regulatory issues, and investment structuring processes for this multi-country initiative that works to increase medical oxygen supply for underserved and peri-urban areas of Sub-Saharan Africa.

Key Contributions:

- Developing a pipeline of three potential franchisees, successfully recruiting three franchisees barely five months on the
 job, and steering franchisee due diligence and contracting.
- Providing technical support to the franchisees on site selection for installation of oxygen production plants, on policy certifications for the plants, and on networking and marketing activities.
- Serving as primary focal point for franchisees, monitoring franchisee performance around production, sales, and distribution, coordinating franchisee training, as well as problem solving, feedback, and review sessions.

Consultant Emergency Nurse | United Nations Office in Nairobi (UNON) August 2020 – January 2021

Worked at the Joint Medical Services Station in Nairobi to provide comprehensive nursing care including medical emergencies and evacuations, vaccinations, COVID-19 management, and tropical/travel medicine services to UN and UN partner agencies' staff in Nairobi and across the region.

Key Contributions:

- Supported the Doctor in providing primary care and treatment to an average of 30 patients per day, including clerking, triaging, diagnosing patients, and providing treatment and medical advice.
- Ordered laboratory tests and conducted phlebotomy procedures.
- Responded to emergency calls at the United Nations Complex in Gigiri, Nairobi.
- Coordinated emergency medical evacuations of regional staff to Nairobi, including COVID-19-related evacuations to the UN COVID Hospital, and liaised with the Ministry of Foreign Affairs for clearance for incoming patients.
- Facilitated patient referrals and admissions and updated referring doctors on patient progress.
- Compiled documents for patients under evacuation, visited hospitalized patients, and wrote reports.
- Served as the COVID-19 liaison, organizing testing for staff and dependents, advising staff and disseminating Ministry of Health guidelines and protocols.
- Carried out travel vaccination and provided travel advice and First Aid kits to staff.
- Prepared statistics on patients attended to at the Joint Medical Services Station and conducted checks on emergency medical equipment.

Nurse Manager - Amref Medical Centre | Amref Health Africa

June 2019 – August 2020

Oversaw day-to-day operations of the clinic while providing leadership in delivery of quality nursing care to an average of 25 patients a day, coordinating occupational health and safety, immunizations and travel medicine, quality assurance in patient care, capacity building and training, patient education, and disease surveillance and outbreak management.

Key Contributions:

- Managed 25 Medical Centre staff and up to US\$ 200 000 in annual budgets.
- Ran the clinic, monitored and ensured delivery of quality nursing care and services.
- Embedded and championed quality in patient care with a focus on customer care, adherence to emergency procedures and clinical protocols, and effective incident reporting and management.
- Educated patients on travel vaccines including Typhoid and Cholera, disease patterns at duty stations, and liaised with the Security Desk to ensure staff had all required vaccinations and travel covers prior to deployment.
- Coordinated emergency evacuations of Amref staff in underserved duty stations.
- Served as Triage Nurse in mass casualty incident drill-management, and took part in formulating protocols on mass casualty and pandemic preparedness.
- Steered disease surveillance and outbreak management including Cholera and COVID-19 surveillance, testing, mass campaigns, vaccinations, contact tracing and isolation, patient follow-up, and workplace preparedness.
- Formulated the Centre's policies on sick leave, emergency preparedness, dangerous drug abuse and reporting, ambulance requisition, and handling of death in the Medical Centre.
- Facilitated capacity building and training of departmental heads on clinical governance, and training of the 700 member staff on occupational health and safety.
- Monitored safety standards to ensure compliance with the Occupational Health and Safety Act, reporting accidents and all sentinel events, and ensured staff welfare.
- Pivotal in the roll out of business development and revenue generating initiatives that grew revenues by 40%, including the introduction of First Aid training/First Aid Kits for sale, wellness checks and health talks for corporate clients, establishment of First Aid rooms in companies, and an MOU with an aero-medical evacuation provider.
- Developed and implemented wellness packages and activities for Amref staff and partner organizations, and delivered health talks to staff and partners on various topical issues including stress and Non-Communicable Diseases management.
- Served as member of the management team, participating in various Clinic committees such as the Occupational Health and Safety Committee, and the Medical Insurance Committee.
- Delivered trainings to public, private, and non-profit organizations (Safarilink, Air Kenya, IRC, Kenya Wildlife Service, Ford Foundation, Born Free Institution, and schools) on First Aid, Basic Life Support, and Advanced Cardiac Life Support.
- Transitioned the Centre from a staff clinic to a social enterprise to ensure sustainability.

Project Manager – AMREF J&J Nursing Oncology Project (Stretch Assignment) | Amref Health Africa February 2020 – October 2020

Served on a stretch assignment to steer the planning, implementation, and monitoring and evaluation of this collaborative project between Johnson & Johnson and Amref to promote excellence in oncology nursing and quality care in Kenya, by supporting the training of nurses to bridge the gap in the number of oncology nurses.

Key Contributions:

- Managed 5 staff, institutional partners, and over US\$300 000 in project budgets.
- Developed project concept notes and proposals, successfully securing US\$400 000 in funding from Johnson & Johnson Foundation to support the training of oncology nurses.
- Coordinated fundraising activities, mobilizing US\$163 203 to support the project.
- Managed the project roll out and implementation, developed monitoring and evaluation plans and performance frameworks, and conducted project monitoring and evaluation to assess impact, progress, and identify and address bottlenecks.
- Developed partnerships with public and private stakeholders and institutions including:
 - Ministry of Health, Cancer Control Institute, Amref International University, Nursing Council of Kenya, Moi Teaching & Referral Hospital, Kenya Medical Training College, Kenyatta National Hospital (KNH)/KNH School of Nursing, The Nairobi Hospital College of Health Sciences, Aga Khan Hospital, Nairobi West Hospital, Kenya Hospice.
- Facilitated capacity-building activities for the project team, government, public and private partners including infrastructural improvements to support the project, curriculum development, and accreditation of clinical rotation

facilities for the students.

- Led an operational research to identify the number of oncology nurses in Kenya and the facilities where they work, and lobbied the Nursing Council of Kenya to introduce blended learning during the COVID-19 pandemic.
- Participated in national-level stakeholder meetings and workshops.
- Documented best practices and lessons learned in collaboration with project staff.

Emergency Flight Nurse | AMREF Flying Doctors

March 2013 - June 2019

Provided pre-hospital and emergency life medical assistance to patients (business travelers, leisure travelers, and expatriates) across Africa to manage their care in the field and during transfers by air or ground transport to better healthcare facilities.

Key Contributions:

- Oversaw 5 staff, supported budgeting process for the Unit, and provided financial oversight on a US\$50 000 budget.
- Conducted emergency medical evacuations and provided medical escort to patients on commercial airlines internationally.
- Operated and ran the 24-hour Control Centre that coordinated medical evacuations.
- Ensured emergency equipment care and check to ensure they were operational at all times.
- Arranged patient hospitalization, followed up on patients, and obtained medical information on behalf of international insurance companies (ISOS, Europe Assist, SOS, and On Call International).
- Organized and facilitated payments for ambulance, hospitalization, taxi services, and accommodation for patients and accompanying family members.
- Provided medical support in response to disasters and mass casualty incidents including the Westgate Terror attack in Nairobi, the Silvestone Air Crash at Wilson Airport, and road accidents along Kenya's highways.
- Served as a medical provider for various public events and charities including marathons, public rallies, walks, horse races, and conferences.
- Delivered First Aid, Basic Life Support, and Advanced Cardiac Life Support to public, private, and non-profit organizations.

EARLY CAREER

Radio Room Nurse (Locum) | AMREF Flying Doctors

December 2011 - February 2013

- Received and processed phone calls from clients requiring the organization's services such as medical evacuation requests, ground ambulance requests, and assistance services.
- Prepared quotations for emergency requests for submission to clients, and followed up on inpatients to provide insurance medical progress.

Nurse – Intensive Care Unit (ICU) | The Nairobi Hospital

November 2008 – February 2013

- Prepared equipment prior to patient admission in the ICU, including ventilator, monitors, and infusion pumps.
- Facilitated patient admissions to the ICU, conducted clinical assessments, performed intubations, and provided care to mechanically ventilated patients.
- Responded to emergencies in the Medical Ward, Surgical ward, Children's Ward, Cancer Ward, as well as the Renal Unit, Radiology, Lab, Physiotherapy, and outpatient clinics.
- Carried out physical assessments of patients, monitored patient vitals, and reported to the doctor.
- Administered drugs and vaccines to patients and monitored patients for adverse events.
- Participated in major and minor diagnoses in the ICU and worked within a multi-disciplinary team to carry out complex
 procedures such as cardiopulmonary resuscitation, defibrillation, cardioversion, coronary angiogram, tracheostomy,
 dialysis/dialysis access insertion, and bronchoscopes.
- Performed arterial blood gas and lab tests and took part in interpreting X-rays in the ward.
- Served as Team Leader during shifts, supervising up to 12 staff, and coordinated the orientation of 6 junior staff in the ICU.
- Provided emotional and psychological support to patients, family, and staff.

Volunteer Nurse - United Nations Joint Medical Services | United Nations Office in Nairobi (UNON) July 2009

- Managed the H1N1 hotline, receiving and answering questions from UNON staff about the flu, and educating staff on precautionary measures during the pandemic.
- Referred suspected cases of H1N1 to the doctor for diagnosis and treatment, and followed up on patients with symptoms.
- Served as a Triage Nurse in the mass casualty incident-drill that evaluated UNON's mass-casualty incidence preparedness.

Nurse – General Ward | The Nairobi Hospital

August 2008 - November 2008

- Diagnosed and treated minor illnesses while attending to an average of 30 patients per day.
- Provided rehabilitation services and nursing care to psychiatry patients.
- Coordinated Maternal and Child Health and Family Planning services in partnership with community-health extension workers and community volunteers, and filed reports with the Public Health Department.
- Provided antenatal and postnatal nursing care and took part in deliveries.

Clinic Nurse - Orthopaedic & Trauma Unit | The Nairobi Hospital Doctors' Plaza March 2008 - August 2008

- Clerked and attended to an average of 20 patients per day.
- Conducted ward rounds and wrote patient case histories.
- Performed wound dressing and removal of casts, stitches, and clips after orthopaedic surgery.
- Provided health advice and education to orthopaedic patients and monitored patient vitals.

EDUCATION & TRAINING

MBA in Healthcare Management – Strathmore University, Kenya (February 2019 – Present)

Bachelor of Science in Nursing – University of Nairobi, Kenya/Amref Virtual Training School (November 2012 – December 2016)

Higher Diploma in Critical Care Nursing – The Nairobi Hospital Cicely McDonnell School of Nursing (March 2011 – March 2012)

Diploma in Nursing – The Nairobi Hospital Cicely McDonnell School of Nursing (March 2005 – March 2008)

Certificate in French: DELF Level A1 – Alliance Française (January 2010 – November 2010)

Certificate in Computer Studies – Hosannah Computers and Agri & Eng Consultants (December 2003 – March 2004)

Professional Development

- European Pediatrics Life Support Aga Khan University Hospital (December 2018)
- Training in Phlebotomy The Nairobi Hospital School of Nursing (January 2018)
- Basic Life Support National Resuscitation Council of Kenya (May 2017)
- Pre-Hospital Trauma Life Support National Association of Emergency Medical Technicians (July 2017)
- Emergency Aircraft Evacuation Procedure Ninety-Nine-Certified KCAA/RCAA/UCAA/TCAA/IATA/ICAO/JAR-OPS Certified Instructor (July 2017)
- Advanced Cardiac Life Support (ACLS) National Resuscitation Council of Kenya (February 2020)
- Trauma Nursing Care Emergency Nurses Association, ENA (August 2014)
- Clinical Consideration in Aero-Medical Transport University of Surrey, UK/Royal College of Physicians, London (July 2014)
- Crew Resource Management Think Aviation Training (May 2014)
- Advanced Trauma Life Support The Nairobi Hospital College of Health Sciences (May 2010)

LICENSURE & PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS

Licensure: Kenya Registered Nurse (KRN) - Nursing Council of Kenya

Licensure: Kenya Registered Clinical Care Nurse – Nursing Council of Kenya

Licensure: Kenya Registered Bachelor of Science in Nursing – Nursing Council of Kenya

Member – Critical Nurses Association of Kenya

Member – Nurses Association of Kenya

Secretary General – AMREF Staff Welfare (January 2018 – January 2020)

REFERENCES

Dr. Joseph Lelo

Medical director, Amref Medical Centre/Amref Flying Doctors, Nairobi

Tel: +254 (0)722 456 860 | Email: joseph.lelo@flydoc.org

Dr. Catherine Kanari

Clinical Business Lead, Amref Medical Centre/ Amref Enterprise, Nairobi

Tel: +254 (0)722 872 186 | Email: Catherine.Kanari@Amref.org

Micah Matiang'i

Principal Tutor, AMREF International University, Nairobi

Tel: +254 (0)20 699 3219 | Email: Micah.Matiangi@Amref.org

Dr. Charles Kariuki

Interventional Cardiologist, The Nairobi Hospital

Tel: +254 (0)733 320 095 | Email: ck1sk@silverstenkariuki.com